<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><itineraries>
<itinerary id="boorsch">
<title>Beatrizet and the Speculum</title>
<author>Suzanne Boorsch</author>
<role>Robert L. Solley Curator of Prints, Drawings, and Photographs,
Yale University Art Gallery</role>
<email/>
<summary>Arriving in Rome around 1540, Nicolas Beatrizet, a young
engraver from the Duchy of Lorraine, soon was hired by Antonio Salamanca
and then also by his chief rival Antonio Lafreri to make plates of Roman
monuments. These two publishers finally, in 1553, had the good sense to
join forces. Beatrizet also worked with two other publishers before
1558, the year he began to publish his own plates. Beatrizet made fewer
prints than has generally been assumed: some forty 16th-century Italian
prints with no indication as to engraver, many often found in Speculum
compilations, have been attributed to him, but analysis strongly
suggests that Beatrizet signed or monogrammed every plate he made. This
itinerary―chronological rather than geographical―will follow
Beatrizet's work through a dozen productive years.</summary>

<!-- 1 -->

<slide>
<title>The Pantheon 1549</title>
<name>A15</name>
<description><![CDATA[<textformat leftmargin="5" rightmargin="5" leading="5"><p align="right">previous | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p><br/><p><b><font color="#ebe3cc">The Pantheon 1549</font></b></p><br/><p>Today known only as a major monument of ancient Rome, in 609 the
structure was consecrated as a church, dedicated to Mary and all the
Christian martyrs. At this time Salamanca and Lafreri were in business
separately, and Beatrizet engraved images of the Pantheon for both.
First Lafreri hired Beatrizet to make a quite straightforward view of
the structure. This presumably was popular, because soon afterward
Salamanca engaged him to make an engraving of the same monument, which
included the two lions and the sarcophagus that are still visible in
front of the building. Lafreri, not to be outdone, reissued his print in
the form you see here, with a small plate added at the bottom, providing
still <i>more</i> information―a view of one of the lions from the
back, the sarcophagus from its end, and an antique vase not shown in the
Salamanca print at all. Beatrizet's monogram was at the lower left in
the original but was obscured when the new plate was added.</p><br/><p><b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0015">More about
A15</a></font></b></p><br/><p align="right">previous | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p></textformat>]]></description>
<pid>speculum-0015-001</pid>
</slide>

<!-- 2 -->

<slide>
<title>The Farnese Palace 1549</title>
<name>A63</name>
<description><![CDATA[<textformat leftmargin="5" rightmargin="5" leading="5"><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p><br/><p><b><font color="#ebe3cc">The Farnese Palace 1549</font></b></p><br/><p>Buyers of souvenir prints from Rome were interested not only in
ancient monuments, but also in the luxurious new palaces built for the
ruling families in the "modern," i.e. classical, style. The Farnese
palace was commissioned from Antonio da Sangallo by Cardinal Alessandro
Farnese around 1515, but was still unfinished at Sangallo's death in
1546.  By this time Alessandro Farnese had been elected as Pope Paul
III, and he commissioned Michelangelo to finish the work. About 1546
Michelangelo designed the huge cornice that imparts a majestic grandeur
to the building and also the balconied opening in the second story,
crowned by the papal coat of arms. Just as for the images of the
Pantheon, Beatrizet was hired by the two rival publishers: in this
instance the undated plate for Salamanca, in which the shadows fall to
the right, was probably first; this one, with shadows to the left, is
dated 1549.</p><br/><p><b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0063">More about
A63</a></font></b></p><br/><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p></textformat>]]></description>
<pid>speculum-0063-001</pid>
</slide>

<!-- 3 -->

<slide>
<title>Fall of Phaeton c. 1550?</title>
<name>A152</name>
<description><![CDATA[<textformat leftmargin="5" rightmargin="5" leading="5"><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p><br/><p><b><font color="#ebe3cc">Fall of Phaeton c. 1550?</font></b></p><br/><p>Michelangelo was the undisputed star of contemporary art in the
middle of the sixteenth century in Rome, and Beatrizet engraved six of
his drawings or paintings, plus the statue of the <i>Risen Christ</i>
(an engraving of this statue, by Jan de Bisschop, is no. <b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0976">C976</a></font></b> in the
Chicago Speculum). This <i>Fall of Phaeton</i>, reproducing a drawing
made for Tommaso Cavalieri about 1533, may not have been originally done
by Beatrizet, since it is inscribed: N BEATRIZET LOTAR RESTITUIT, "N
Beatrizet of Lorraine restored it," but the original engraver is
unknown.  Also unknown is the route by which Michelangelo's compositions
reached the publisher and/or engraver―no document attests to
Michelangelo having had any particular relationship with a publisher,
and Michelangelo, in fact, is known to have made disdainful remarks
about prints.  The image apparently continued to be in demand for more
than two hundred years, as is made evident by the date of 1773 put on
the plate by the publisher Carlo Losi.</p><br/><p><b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0152">More about
A152</a></font></b></p><br/><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p></textformat>]]></description>
<pid>speculum-0152-001</pid>
</slide>

<!-- 4 -->

<slide>
<title>Temple of Fortuna Virilis 1550</title>
<name>B180</name>
<description><![CDATA[<textformat leftmargin="5" rightmargin="5" leading="5"><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p><br/><p><b><font color="#ebe3cc">Temple of Fortuna Virilis 1550</font></b></p><br/><p>This exquisite little temple was also used as a church in the
medieval and Renaissance eras, dedicated to Saint Mary of Egypt, as the
inscription indicates.   It was published, in 1550, by yet another of
the men Beatrizet worked for, Tommaso Barlacchi, for whom Beatrizet had
made three plates back in 1541, of figural subjects by Raphael. The
plates Beatrizet made for Barlacchi were smaller than those he did for
other publishers, perhaps indicating that Barlacchi had a smaller press.
The Jubilee year at mid century would have brought thousands of
pilgrims―potential customers for prints―to Rome, although
this is Beatrizet's only plate actually bearing that date. Beatrizet's
monogram, "N. B. F." ("F" for <i>fecit</i>, "made") is at the bottom of
the plinth supporting the leftmost column. Engraved in very regular
slanting strokes, the plate shows Beatrizet in complete command of his
technique.</p><br/><p><b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0180">More about
B180</a></font></b></p><br/><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p></textformat>]]></description>
<pid>speculum-0180-001</pid>
</slide>

<!-- 5 -->

<slide>
<title>Circus Maximus 1553</title>
<name>A48</name>
<description><![CDATA[<textformat leftmargin="5" rightmargin="5" leading="5"><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p><br/><p><b><font color="#ebe3cc">Circus Maximus 1553</font></b></p><br/><p>By the 1550s scholarly antiquarianism had a vogue of immense
proportions in Rome. The Neapolitan Pirro Ligorio, artist and architect,
was also the leading antiquarian and archaeologist of the mid-sixteenth
century, and Beatrizet's engraving is based on Ligorio's reconstruction
of a model―in wax according to the lengthy inscription on the
print―of the Circus Maximus, following ancient authors. The detail
and accuracy of the reconstruction are impressive: it shows the long
central barrier (<i>spina</i>) flanked by arches supporting three cones,
the barrier itself with its large and smaller Egyptian obelisks with
hieroglyphs, temples to the sun, the moon, and Neptune, smaller statues,
and triumphal arches.  The Circus was used primarily for chariot racing,
and three quadrigas are seen on the near side of the course. Michele
Tramezzini was a publisher established in Venice, but his brother
Francesco was in Rome, and the print proclaims that it was sanctioned by
Pope Julius III.  This plate is among the largest generally made at this
era; the dimensions may well reflect the upper limits in the size of
presses of the time.</p><br/><p><b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0048">More about
A48</a></font></b></p><br/><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p></textformat>]]></description>
<pid>speculum-0048-001</pid>
</slide>

<!-- 6 -->

<slide>
<title>Relief on the Arch of Constantine 1553</title>
<name>A97</name>
<description><![CDATA[<textformat leftmargin="5" rightmargin="5" leading="5"><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p><br/><p><b><font color="#ebe3cc">Relief on the Arch of Constantine 1553</font></b></p><br/><p>The same growing antiquarian interest that led to Tramezzini's
publication of the plates of the Circus Flaminius and Circus Maximus
inspired Lafreri to commission images of ancient bas reliefs, like this
section of a Trajanic frieze showing the emperor's victorious combat
over the Dacians, which had been incorporated into the Arch of
Constantine.  Dated 1553, this plate manifests a suppleness in the
handling of the burin that increased in Beatrizet's work over the course
of the 1550s.  Another plate in the Chicago Speculum (<b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0098">A98</a></font></b>) of one of these
Trajanic reliefs in the Arch of Constantine has been thought to
constitute a pair with this engraving and also to have been made by
Beatrizet, but that one has no signature or monogram, it is slightly
smaller, and the subject is reversed whereas Beatrizet's print
represents the relief in its true direction.</p><br/><p><b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0097">More about
A97</a></font></b></p><br/><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p></textformat>]]></description>
<pid>speculum-0097-001</pid>
</slide>

<!-- 7 -->

<slide>
<title>Castel Sant'Angelo, first state</title>
<name>A26</name>
<description><![CDATA[<textformat leftmargin="5" rightmargin="5" leading="5"><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p><br/><p><b><font color="#ebe3cc">Castel Sant'Angelo, first state</font></b></p><br/><p>The building known as the Castel Sant'Angelo was originally built by
the emperor Hadrian as a mausoleum for himself and his family. Later it
was used by the popes as a castle and fortress. The second state of
Beatrizet's print (<b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0046">A46</a></font></b>)
has been thought to be a copy of the first (<b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0026">A26</a></font></b>), but close
examination reveals that the two prints were pulled from the same plate.
The confusion is understandable, because the plate underwent extensive
reworking in its second state, some thirty years after the first. The
engraving was originally made during the pontificate of Pius IV, between
1559 and 1565, as is shown by the Medici coat of arms above the arched
doorway leading from the rampart at the left, and on the banner flying
above. Later the Sfondrati coat of arms of Pope Gregory XIV (r. 1590-91)
was substituted in those two places.  Those changes, however, were just
the beginning. The fortification to the right of the print underwent a
notable change of shape―although the original outlines can still
be discerned, further evidence that the prints are from the same
plate―and a great deal of crosshatching was added, increasing the
contrast of the image but also stiffening Beatrizet's more fluid lines.
Sections of the plate that were not touched, however, as for instance
the lettering, can clearly be seen to be identical in the two
prints.</p><br/><p><b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0026">More about
A26</a></font></b></p><br/><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p></textformat>]]></description>
<pid>speculum-0026-001</pid>
</slide>

<slide>
<title>Castel Sant'Angelo, second state</title>
<name>A46</name>
<description><![CDATA[<textformat leftmargin="5" rightmargin="5" leading="5"><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p><br/><p><b><font color="#ebe3cc">Castel Sant'Angelo, second state</font></b></p><br/><p>(Compare this print of the Castel Sant'Angelo with the previous
print, A26.)</p><br/><p><b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0046">More about
A46</a></font></b></p><br/><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p></textformat>]]></description>
<pid>speculum-0046-001</pid>
</slide>

<!-- 8 -->

<slide>
<title>Battle of the Amazons 1559</title>
<name>A100, A101</name>
<description><![CDATA[<textformat leftmargin="5" rightmargin="5" leading="5"><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p><br/><p><b><font color="#ebe3cc">Battle of the Amazons 1559</font></b></p><br/><p>Beatrizet's second-largest work is this image, on two plates, of a
sarcophagus showing the Battle of the Amazons.  (His largest work is his
engraving on ten plates of Michelangelo's <i>Last Judgment</i>, which he
made in 1562, copying the engraving made in the late 1540s by Giorgio
Ghisi.) In 1558 Beatrizet had issued an engraving of the siege by the
French of Thionville, in his native Lorraine; that was his first dated
print indicating that he was not only the engraver of the plate, but
also its publisher.  From that time onward, Beatrizet did no more work
for other publishers. In the bottom margin of this masterful engraving
is the proud inscription: "Nicolas Beatrizet from Lorraine engraved this
Battle of the Amazons from an antique sarcophagus visible on the
Capitoline, and published it at his own expense for the good of all
those who take pleasure in antique things".  It is precisely dated to
the Kalends of January 1559.</p><br/><p>More about
<b><font color="#df790c"><a
href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0100">A100</a></font></b>, <b><font
color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=0101">A101</a></font></b></p><br/><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p></textformat>]]></description>
<pid>speculum-1100-001</pid>
</slide>

<!-- 9 -->

<slide>
<title>Ocean 1560</title>
<name>A125</name>
<description><![CDATA[<textformat leftmargin="5" rightmargin="5" leading="5"><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | next</p><br/><p><b><font color="#ebe3cc">Ocean 1560</font></b></p><br/><p>The last of Beatrizet's engravings on this itinerary depicts a statue
of a reclining Oceanus, excavated in 1556. Beatrizet rendered the statue
reversed from its true direction. According to the inscription it was
found near the place where the statues of the river gods Nile and Tiber
had been dug up many years previously. Also according to the
inscription, at the date Beatrizet made this engraving, 1560, the statue
was in the possession of Giovanni Battista and Giovanni Vincenzo Fabio;
it was later acquired by Cardinal Alessandro Farnese (grandson of Pope
Paul III, who had built the Farnese Palace, see <b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0063">A63</a></font></b> above) and
eventually went with the Farnese collection to Naples. Because of the
similarity of this subject to the river gods Nile and Tiber, and perhaps
because those statues are mentioned in the inscription here, the
anonymous engravings of those sculptures (<b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0108">A108</a></font></b>, <b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0109">A109</a></font></b>) have been
attributed to Beatrizet, but those prints―delightful as they are
with their depictions of a sphinx and putti climbing on the Nile,
Romulus and Remus and the wolf with the Tiber, and the reliefs on their
bases shown around three sides―are engraved with a harder
technique than Beatrizet's relaxed and supple line.  There still remains
ample work for scholars to sort out the hands of the many anonymous
engravers of prints that found their way into Speculum collections.</p><br/><p><b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0125">More about
A125</a></font></b></p><br/><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | next</p></textformat>]]></description>
<pid>speculum-0125-001</pid>
</slide>
</itinerary>
</itineraries>
