<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><itineraries>

<itinerary id="campidoglio">

<title>The Campidoglio Engraved</title>
<author>Rebecca Zorach</author>
<role>Associate Professor of Art History, University of Chicago</role>
<email>rezorach@uchicago.edu</email>
<summary>The changing face of the Campidoglio in Rome, also known as the
ancient Capitoline Hill, reinvented in the Renaissance and home to a collection
of important ancient statues.</summary>

<!-- 1 -->

<slide>
<title>Approaching the Campidoglio</title>
<name>B185</name>
<description><![CDATA[<textformat leftmargin="5" rightmargin="5" leading="5"><p align="right">previous | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p><br/><p><b><font color="#ebe3cc">Approaching the Campidoglio</font></b></p><br/><p>The Capitoline hill was one of the famed seven hills of Rome, and gives us
the word "Capitol" for the seat of the US government in Washington, D.C. In the
Renaissance (as today), it was known in Italian as the Campidoglio.</p><br/><p>This lovely etched view by Willem van Nieuwlandt, who published a series of
prints of Roman scenes in Antwerp, shows how one might approach the Capitoline
hill from the Roman Forum, via the slightly winding path leading up the incline
on the left. To the right is the arch of Septimius Severus.</p><br/><p>Van Nieuwlandt, a Dutch artist (1584-ca. 1635) was one of many northern
artists who traveled to Rome and made sketches of the sights there.</p><br/><p><b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0185">More about
B185</a></font></b></p><br/><p align="right">previous | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p></textformat>]]></description>
<pid>speculum-0185-001</pid>
</slide>

<!-- 2 -->

<slide>
<title>A Renaissance view of the ancient city</title>
<name>A4</name>
<description><![CDATA[<textformat leftmargin="5" rightmargin="5" leading="5"><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p><br/><p><b><font color="#ebe3cc">A Renaissance view of the ancient city</font></b></p><br/><p>This Renaissance map presents a conjectural view of ancient Rome stressing
topographic relief―in other words, the seven hills. It shows a rather bare
area labeled "Capitolium" that includes the Temple of Jupiter and little
else―reflecting Renaissance uncertainty about exactly what buildings would
have been situated where in ancient times. ( <b><font color="#df790c"><a href="event:zoom? x=0.112&amp;y=-0.075&amp;zoom=50">Take a closer look.
</a></font></b> )</p><br/><p>Renaissance antiquarians considered the Capitoline Hill to be the most
prominent, and first settled, of the ancient city. This is reflected in
Renaissance visions of the earliest history of the city, depicting a square
layout in which only the Capitoline and Palatine Hills are enclosed within the
city walls.</p><br/><p>This map is a copy, engraved by Ambrogio Brambilla and published by Claudio
Duchetti, of an earlier map engraved by Etienne Dupérac and published by
Antonio Lafreri. Lafreri was Duchetti's uncle and the publisher of the Speculum
Romanae Magnificentiae prints. He also published numerous maps, many of which
were often bound together in similar collections known as the Geographia.</p><br/><p>For an entirely different view of the ancient Capitol, see the next image.</p><br/><p><b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0004">More about
A4</a></font></b></p><br/><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p></textformat>]]></description>
<pid>speculum-0004-001</pid>
</slide>

<!-- 3 -->

<slide>
<title>The ancient Capitol in action</title>
<name>D994</name>
<description><![CDATA[<textformat leftmargin="5" rightmargin="5" leading="5"><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p><br/><p><b><font color="#ebe3cc">The ancient Capitol in action</font></b></p><br/><p>This is a very large engraving, made up of three folio-sized sheets joined
together. It represents a rather fantastical Renaissance view of the ancient
Roman Capitol: it  looks more like a stage set with actors (including gods such
as Mercury and Cupid) than a scholarly, classical view of the ancient city. It
also recalls other prints that depict scenes of everyday life in the early
Renaissance. The theatricality of this image carries over into others that use
the backdrop of Rome to stage dramas of various kinds [see exhibition case
24].</p><br/><p>We do not know what artist designed or engraved this beguiling image.
Impressions (copies) of it often appear in Speculum Romanae
Magnificentiae collections; it was published by Antonio Salamanca, the
print publisher, originally from Spain, who was Antonio Lafreri's
sometime rival and later business partner.</p><br/><p><b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0994">More about
D994</a></font></b></p><br/><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p></textformat>]]></description>
<pid>speculum-0994-001</pid>
</slide>

<!-- 4 -->

<slide>
<title>A map of Renaissance Rome</title>
<name>A3</name>
<description><![CDATA[<textformat leftmargin="5" rightmargin="5" leading="5"><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p><br/><p><b><font color="#ebe3cc">A map of Renaissance Rome</font></b></p><br/><p>This map provides a panoramic view of the city in the late sixteenth
century. A legend at the bottom of the map indicates the main features by
category―temples, streets, etc. On the Campidoglio, a label indicates the
equestrian statue of Marcus Aurelius that was (and still is) the centerpiece of
the piazza: "Statua Marci Aurelii." ( <b><font color="#df790c"><a href="event:zoom?x=-0.139&amp;y=0.127&amp;zoom=50">Take a
closer look.</a></font></b> ) For more on this
statue, see the next two images.</p><br/><p>Note that a later viewer has added annotations to the map and colored the
Tiber blue. Several of the prints in the Speculum collection at Columbia
University's Avery Library also have water that has been colored blue. Both
collections were sold by the same book dealer in Berlin (S. Calvary
&amp; Co.), in
the late nineteenth century; this might suggest that all the Chicago and
Columbia prints were once part of a single gigantic collection, or that the
blue-colored prints in particular belonged to one person and were acquired by
Calvary and then split between two different lots.</p><br/><p><b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0003">More about
A3</a></font></b></p><br/><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p></textformat>]]></description>
<pid>speculum-0003-001</pid>
</slide>

<!-- 5 -->

<slide>
<title>The statue of Marcus Aurelius</title>
<name>A135</name>
<description><![CDATA[<textformat leftmargin="5" rightmargin="5" leading="5"><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p><br/><p><b><font color="#ebe3cc">The statue of Marcus Aurelius</font></b></p><br/><p>The equestrian statue of the philosopher-emperor, Marcus Aurelius, is the
centerpiece of the Piazza del Campidoglio. During the Middle Ages, it was
thought to be a statue of Constantine, the first Christian emperor of Rome.
This probably accounts for the survival of the statue during a period in which
other bronze statues, viewed as pagan idols, were melted down and reused as raw
material.</p><br/><p>In the Renaissance it was a new arrival to the site. The statue was moved to
the Campidoglio from the piazza in front of the church of San Giovanni in
Laterano in 1538 by Pope Paul III, as part of plans for a new design for the
area. Michelangelo produced the overall design, but was not thrilled at having
to incorporate the statue. Nonetheless, he provided the statue's pedestal as
part of his new design.</p><br/><p>Traditionally the design is understood to have been commissioned by Paul III
in preparation for his meeting with the Holy Roman Emperor Charles V in 1536 (a
reconciliation between the empire and the papacy after the 1527 Sack of Rome).
But evidence suggests that the Roman civic government also played a major role;
the  area was, in fact, devoted to civic and not papal concerns.</p><br/><p>It took many years and the contribution of many builders for the square to
acquire any semblance of Michelangelo's plans for it.</p><br/><p>Today the original statue is housed in the Capitoline museum, and a copy
stands in its place.</p><br/><p><b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0135">More about
A135</a></font></b></p><br/><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p></textformat>]]></description>
<pid>speculum-0135-001</pid>
</slide>

<!-- 6 -->

<slide>
<title>Another view of the statue of Marcus Aurelius</title>
<name>C826</name>
<description><![CDATA[<textformat leftmargin="5" rightmargin="5" leading="5"><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p><br/><p><b><font color="#ebe3cc">Another view of the statue of Marcus Aurelius</font></b></p><br/><p>The previous image displayed the side of Michelangelo's pedestal that
identified the statue as that of Marcus Aurelius. In this one, we see the
inscription that appears on the opposite side of the pedestal from the
preceding image. What is strange is that the statue retains the same
orientation, with the horse and rider facing to the left. If it is the opposite
side of the statue, we should see the horse and rider facing the other way.</p><br/><p>This may be the result of the artist's drawing being reversed when turned
into a print, since printing plates were oriented in reverse vis-a-vis the
printed images they produced. The text on the pedestal, however, has been
carefully (if not too adeptly) copied so as to appear correctly oriented in the
resulting engraving. This image, part of a large set of engravings of statues
that are organized by their location at the time the set was produced, appears
in a sub-grouping of statues located at the Campidoglio, in the open air or in
the Palazzo dei Conservatori (the seat of Rome's municipal government).</p><br/><p>The inscription cites two popes, Paul III, who had the statue moved to the
Campidoglio, and Sixtus IV, who had had the statue reinstalled at the Lateran
in the late fifteenth century.</p><br/><p><b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0826">More about
C826</a></font></b></p><br/><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p></textformat>]]></description>
<pid>speculum-0826-001</pid>
</slide>

<!-- 7 -->

<slide>
<title>Map of Rome</title>
<name>B287</name>
<description><![CDATA[<textformat leftmargin="5" rightmargin="5" leading="5"><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p><br/><p><b><font color="#ebe3cc">Map of Rome</font></b></p><br/><p>This map was published around 1597 but was likely copied from an earlier
map, so it is not up to date. It shows schematically the beginnings of the
implementation of the Renaissance plan for the site: the statue of Marcus
Aurelius stands within the oval area that Michelangelo designed for the piazza.
With some inaccuracies (partly due to the small scale), it corresponds
approximately to the view in the next image, which was made around 1560.
( <b><font color="#df790c"><a href="event:zoom?x=-0.096&amp;y=0.0290&amp;zoom=74">
Take a closer look.</a></font></b> )</p><br/><p><b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0287">More about
B287</a></font></b></p><br/><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p></textformat>]]></description>
<pid>speculum-0287-001</pid>
</slide>

<!-- 8 -->

<slide>
<title>The Campidoglio around 1560</title>
<name>A65</name>
<description><![CDATA[<textformat leftmargin="5" rightmargin="5" leading="5"><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p><br/><p><b><font color="#ebe3cc">The Campidoglio around 1560</font></b></p><br/><p>This engraving has been attributed to Nicolas Beatrizet, a printmaker from
Lorraine who worked in Rome and frequently produced prints published by Antonio
Lafreri. It shows the Campidoglio around 1560. The Palazzo Senatorio, to the
rear, has a new staircase designed by Michelangelo, with a reclining river
statue on either side, but no other updates.</p><br/><p>The Palazzo dei Conservatori, to the right, also retains its earlier facade
(in fact, the image presents it with a simplified version; it had twelve
archways, not six).</p><br/><p>The colossal head of Constantine, fragment of a gigantic ancient sculpture,
peeks out of the portico of the Palazzo dei Conservatori, on the right and to
the rear.</p><br/><p>Note the changes that take place in the rear and right palaces between this
image and the next.</p><br/><p><b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0065">More about
A65</a></font></b></p><br/><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p></textformat>]]></description>
<pid>speculum-0065-001</pid>
</slide>

<!-- 9 -->

<slide>
<title>"As it is now"</title>
<name>A77</name>
<description><![CDATA[<textformat leftmargin="5" rightmargin="5" leading="5"><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p><br/><p><b><font color="#ebe3cc">"As it is now"</font></b></p><br/><p>Nicolaus van Aelst was a Flemish engraver who published copies of Speculum
prints, and also his own depicting Roman obelisks, churches, and other sites,
in the late sixteenth and early seventeenth centuries. This one is dated 1600.
The print is labeled "Capitolii Romani vera imago ut nunc est," meaning "True
image of the Roman Capitol as it is now." This title suggests an acute
awareness of the changing face of Rome's urban landscape at the end of the
sixteenth century, and the demand by visitors and collectors for accurate
representations of the scene that they themselves saw on the spot.</p><br/><p>To the rear, the Palazzo Senatorio (the Senate palace), and to the right,
the Palazzo dei Conservatori (the seat of Roman civic government), were built
in the later sixteenth century. To the left, the statue called "Marforio" [A113
link?] appears, restored and installed as a fountain; it was placed there in
1594, by the architect Giacomo della Porta, with the patronage of Pope Clement
VIII. The fountain sits at the future site of the Palazzo Nuovo, which appears
completed in the next image in the itinerary; the Marforio fountain
was removed in the mid-seventeenth century, and eventually placed inside the
palazzo.</p><br/><p><b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0077">More about
A77</a></font></b></p><br/><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p></textformat>]]></description>
<pid>speculum-0077-001</pid>
</slide>

<!-- 10 -->

<slide>
<title>The mid-seventeenth century and the de' Rossi</title>
<name>A78</name>
<description><![CDATA[<textformat leftmargin="5" rightmargin="5" leading="5"><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p><br/><p><b><font color="#ebe3cc">The mid-seventeenth century and the de' Rossi</font></b></p><br/><p>In this updated version of the previous engraving, the piazza appears in the
form in which it would remain for approximately three hundred years. The three
palazzi have been completed and the oval at the center of the piazza has been
paved with a radiating pattern.</p><br/><p>This print was published by Giovanni Giacomo de' Rossi, member of the
family that dominated print publishing in Rome in the seventeenth
century. De' Rossi apparently acquired Nicolaus van Aelst's copper plate
(see <b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0077">A77</a></font></b>) and had
portions of it re-engraved to update the scene―in particular,
adding the Palazzo Nuovo to the left and the paved pattern on the
ground. This was one among many plates that he acquired and republished
under his name.</p><br/><p>Michelangelo's paving stone design had actually been much more complex, an
elaborate design of intersecting arcs that was never carried out under the
popes, perhaps because it was perceived to have  questionable symbolism. Only
under Mussolini, in 1940, was the design implemented, as part of the Fascist
reinvention of Roman classicism. ( <b><font color="#df790c"><a href="assets/campidoglio-1.html" target="_blank">Click here for a modern
view.</a></font></b> )</p><br/><p><b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0078">More about
A78</a></font></b></p><br/><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p></textformat>]]></description>
<pid>speculum-0078-001</pid>
</slide>

<!-- 11 -->

<slide>
<title>The Tiber</title> 
<name>C805</name>
<description><![CDATA[<textformat leftmargin="5" rightmargin="5" leading="5"><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p><br/><p><b><font color="#ebe3cc">The Tiber</font></b></p><br/><p>This print depicts the statue of a personification of the Tiber river
installed under the staircase of the Palazzo Senatorio, visible in several of
the views in this itinerary. As the inscription notes, it was originally a
representation of the Tigris in Mesopotamia, but was changed into a
representation of the Tiber with the addition of a wolf nursing the young
Romulus and Remus, founders of Rome. For an image of the famous statue of the
wolf, which also stands in the Campidoglio, see the next image.</p><br/><p>Giovanni Battista Cavalieri published engravings of many of the most famous
statues of Roman antiquity. His collection was later expanded and republished
by several other publishers. They are organized by the collection in which the
statues are found, so the statues at the Campidoglio are grouped together
(Chicago Speculum
<b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0804">C804</a></font></b>,
<b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0805">C805</a></font></b>,
<b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0806">C806</a></font></b>,
<b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0807">C807</a></font></b>,
<b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0826">C826</a></font></b>,
<b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0827">C827</a></font></b>,
<b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0828">C828</a></font></b>,
<b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0829">C829</a></font></b>,
<b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0830">C830</a></font></b>,
<b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0831">C831</a></font></b>, 
<b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0832">C832</a></font></b>, 
<b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0833">C833</a></font></b>, 
<b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0834">C834</a></font></b>, 
<b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0835">C835</a></font></b>)</p><br/><p><b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0805">More about
C805</a></font></b></p><br/><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p></textformat>]]></description>
<pid>speculum-0805-001</pid>
</slide>

<!-- 12 -->

<slide>
<title>The Capitoline Wolf</title>

<name>B347</name>
<description><![CDATA[<textformat leftmargin="5" rightmargin="5" leading="5"><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | next</p><br/><p><b><font color="#ebe3cc">The Capitoline Wolf</font></b></p><br/><p>This print depicts one of the most famous statues on the Campidoglio. The
bronze statue represents a female wolf nursing the founders of Rome, Romulus
and Remus. The two infants were added to this ancient Etruscan statue in the
fifteenth century, probably in order to reinforce its association with the
city's origin myth and its power as a symbol of Rome.</p><br/><p>Other sculptures associated with the Campidoglio include the
"Spinario" (<b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0114">A114</a></font></b>); the
Trophies of Marius (
<b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0123">A123</a></font></b>, 
<b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0124">A124</a></font></b>, 
<b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0351">B351</a></font></b>, 
<b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0352">B352</a></font></b>); Roma Victrix (
<b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0090">A90</a></font></b>); the Triumph of
Marcus Aurelius (
<b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0116">A116</a></font></b>);
the Battle of Amazons (
<b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0110">A100</a></font></b> - 
<b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0101">A101</a></font></b>) and a frieze of
sacrificial instruments (
<b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0128">A128</a></font></b>).</p><br/><p>Bibliography:</p><br/><p>Philipp Fehl, "The Placement of the Equestrian Statue of Marcus Aurelius in
the Middle Ages," in Journal of the Warburg and Courtauld Institutes, Vol. 37,
1974 (1974), pp. 362-367</p><br/><p>Charles Burroughs, "Michelangelo at the Campidoglio: Artistic Identity,
Patronage, and Manufacture," in Artibus et Historiae, Vol. 14, No. 28. (1993),
pp. 85-111.</p><br/><p><b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0347">More about
B347</a></font></b></p><br/><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | next</p></textformat>]]></description>
<pid>speculum-0347-001</pid>
</slide>
</itinerary>
</itineraries>
