<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><itineraries>
<itinerary id="heuer">
<title>Viewing Ruins</title>
<author>Christopher P. Heuer</author>
<role>Assistant Professor, History of Art and Archaeology, Princeton
University</role>
<email>cheuer@princeton.edu</email><!-- do not publish email -->
<summary>Rome's crumbling monuments fascinated Renaissance artists.
For printmakers, the shattered forms of the Colosseum, the
labyrinthine Baths of Diocletian, and fragmentary reliefs strewn
around the Capitoline supplied palpable way to think about the present
as much as the past.</summary>

<!-- 1 -->

<slide>
<title>The Ideal View</title>
<name>A29</name>
<description><![CDATA[<textformat leftmargin="5" rightmargin="5" leading="5"><p align="right">previous | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p><br/><p><b><font color="#ebe3cc">The Ideal View</font></b></p><br/><p>The gigantic Roman amphitheatre known as the Colosseum, begun in 75
AD, was the largest antique building surviving in Renaissance Rome.
Designed to seat more than 70,000 spectators, the elliptical structure
was used for gladiatorial combat and animal fighting until well into
the seventh century.</p><br/><p>By the time this print was published in Rome in 1581 by Claudio
Duchetti, much of the Colosseum's western side had vanished, ravaged
by fire and earthquakes, and carted away by centuries of looters―a
process that was going on continued well into the 1600s. Duchetti's
print, a copy of an earlier Lafreri composition, smooths out the
gaping hole at the building's southwest quadrant. He uses the view to
show both the interior of the Colosseum and the exterior elevation.
Many printmakers were amateur architects, and the cutaway
building appears less as a ruin than a scenographic plan, scoured of
all but he faintest signs of age.</p><br/><p>The print's extraction of the Colosseum it its urban setting can be
contrasted with other, smaller views of the same Colosseum by Northern
artists (cf. <b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0212">B212</a></font></b>, <b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0217">B217</a></font></b>), which often blended
bits of the structure with the landscape, emphasizing its physical
surroundings.</p><br/><p><b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0029">More about
A29</a></font></b></p><br/><p align="right">previous | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p></textformat>]]></description>
<pid>speculum-0029-001</pid>
</slide>

<!-- 2 -->

<slide>
<title>A new kind of landscape</title>
<name>B212</name> 
<description><![CDATA[<textformat leftmargin="5" rightmargin="5" leading="5"><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p><br/><p><b><font color="#ebe3cc">A new kind of landscape</font></b></p><br/><p>This etching was one of twenty-four views of ancient Rome published
by the Antwerp artist Hieronymus Cock (1510-1570).  It shows the
Colosseum glimpsed from ground level, its crumbing façade sprouting
weeks and grass. The low viewpoint and tight cropping monumentalize the
building, emphasizing the idea of a ruin seen, as opposed to just
charted.</p><br/><p>In contrast to other views (e.g. <b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0029">A29</a></font></b>) Cock
scrutinizes the decay of the archways, noting how the edges of masonry
have been chipped, and how the sprigs on the lumpen ground are the same
as those high up in the rotunda. Cock's print suggesting that ruination
is still going on. This is an image of antiquity in the
present―seven birds flutter away, and a draftsman in modern dress
sketches in the immediate foreground.</p><br/><p>Cock journeyed to Rome between 1546-8 intending to study antique
sculpture, but became fascinated with the Palatine monuments, mounting
expeditions to the Colosseum and the Baths of Diocletian.  The drawing
for this print, in reverse, survives now in Edinburgh, and was likely
executed by Cock on the spot.</p><br/><p><b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0212">More about
B212</a></font></b></p><br/><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p></textformat>]]></description>
<pid>speculum-0212-001</pid>
</slide>

<!-- 3 -->

<slide>
<title>Looking inside</title>
<name>B215</name>
<description><![CDATA[<textformat leftmargin="5" rightmargin="5" leading="5"><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p><br/><p><b><font color="#ebe3cc">Looking inside</font></b></p><br/><p>This etching shows a cross-section of the Colosseum, another view
based on a drawing by Cock himself. It combines a glance upwards onto
the upper Corinthian tier with a tunnelling view down into a radial
basement corridor crossed by dark shadows. At the time as he was
publishing his first series of ruins in Antwerp, Cock was also
publishing maps―this etching, however, is oriented horizontally,
making it more like the page of a book.  The inscription "PROSPECTUS"
alerts beholders that the image is a view, rather than a plan.</p><br/><p>In the extreme lower left of the print, next to a date of "1550,"
there is a just-visible number, 1546, which, remarkably, has been
effaced ( <b><font color="#df790c"><a href="event:zoom?x=0.312&amp;y=-0.391&amp;zoom=57">
Take a closer look.</a></font></b> ) Most likely this
number is the date of the original drawing, which Cock erroneously
transferred when he etched the plate.</p><br/><p><b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0215">More about
B215</a></font></b></p><br/><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p></textformat>]]></description>
<pid>speculum-0215-001</pid>
</slide>

<!-- 4 -->

<slide>
<title>Sculptural Subjects</title>
<name>A113</name>
<description><![CDATA[<textformat leftmargin="5" rightmargin="5" leading="5"><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p><br/><p><b><font color="#ebe3cc">Sculptural Subjects</font></b></p><br/><p>Like buildings, antique sculptures in Rome were rarely preserved
intact. This engraving is likely a copy of a 1550 print attributed to
the Lorraine printmaker Nicolas Beatrizet, and shows an allegorical
sculpture known as Marforio. Pendant to the famed Pasquino, the
reclining Marforio was one of the "talking statues" of the sixteenth
century. Disgruntled citizens would post written complaints on the
marbles, denouncing civic injustice or, more often, mount anonymous
critiques of the papacy.</p><br/><p>Duchetti has excised some of the inscriptions that appear in earlier
version of the print, such as that which appears a Florence copy of the
<i>Speculum</i>. Missing both arms, lower legs, and the tip of its nose,
Marforio was probably an allegory of the Tiber River. In the print, a
youth at immediate left, dwarfed by the sculpture's huge bulk,
energetically studies the Marforio with sketchbook in hand.  The
inscription at the center is even a semi-humorous "Marforiade," which,
within the print has the effect of alluding to the very public character
of the sculpture.</p><br/><p><b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0113">More about
A113</a></font></b></p><br/><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p></textformat>]]></description>
<pid>speculum-0113-001</pid>
</slide>

<!-- 5 -->

<slide>
<title>The Septizonium</title>
<name>A11</name>
<description><![CDATA[<textformat leftmargin="5" rightmargin="5" leading="5"><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p><br/><p><b><font color="#ebe3cc">The Septizonium</font></b></p><br/><p>This print records remnants of the so-called Septizonium (or
Septizodium), a strange columnar structure erected on the south Palatine
Hill in 203. Scholars disagree about the function of the building; some
suggest it was intended as a greeting monument for visitors approaching
Rome on the via Appia, to the southwest. In the print, weeds mantle the
cragged top edges of the porches and ivy weaves in and out of the
entablatures, yet the masonry walls are shown surprisingly intact.  This
state was not to last long: Pope Sixtus V destroyed the building
entirely in 1588-9 to construct a new roadway.</p><br/><p>In fact, despite the emergence of building conservation programs as
early as the 1520s, more ancient Roman monuments were actually destroyed
in the Renaissance than in preceding centuries.  The papacy fully
sanctioned digging for gems and sculptures on the Palatine, which
irreversibly weakened many antique structures.  Along with several
architectural drawings from the 1570s, this print by Lafreri was one of
only a few records of the Septizonium to survive.</p><br/><p><b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0011">More about
A11</a></font></b></p><br/><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p></textformat>]]></description>
<pid>speculum-0011-001</pid>
</slide>

<!-- 6 -->

<slide>
<title>A Juxtaposition for Landscape's Sake</title>
<name>B227</name>
<description><![CDATA[<textformat leftmargin="5" rightmargin="5" leading="5"><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p><br/><p><b><font color="#ebe3cc">A Juxtaposition for Landscape's Sake</font></b></p><br/><p>In this etching, Hieronymus Cock imaginatively conjoins two
structures which lay nearly a mile apart from another in Rome, the
Colosseum and the Septizonium.  The siting of the buildings can be
compared with, for example, Lafreri's print in A11. The twin monuments
appear on a ruddy, lumpen hillock at the end of a roadway, where two
onlookers point left and right. The pair functions as a surrogate for
our own view onto the landscape, and rhymes visually with the gigantic
buildings before them.</p><br/><p>This detail of the Colosseum corresponds a drawing now in Berlin by
the Dutch artist Marten van Heemskerck (1498-1574) which Cock might have
known. At least in comparison to Duchetti (cf. <b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0029">A29</a></font></b>), Cock here proves
most interested in landscape effects rather than topographical accuracy.
As in the other prints from the 1551 series, these ruins are depicted in
what the Dutch called <i>schilderachtig</i>, or picturesque mode-less
archaeological sites than pictorial motifs. As a publisher, Cock would
have been well aware of the potential for ruins to appeal to collectors
of art as well as those interested in Rome.</p><br/><p>Along with other sketches this image was republished in three
separate editions by Cock's firm in the Antwerp, <i>Aux Quatre Vents</i>
(At the Sign of the Four Winds).  The series went on to be re-printed in
France and in Italy, and came to exert a lasting influence on landscape
painting from mid-century, informing the work of Pieter Bruegel the
Elder and Veronese.</p><br/><p><b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0227">More about
B227</a></font></b></p><br/><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p></textformat>]]></description>
<pid>speculum-0227-001</pid>
</slide>

<!-- 7 -->

<slide>
<title>Antique time in the present</title>
<name>A120</name>
<description><![CDATA[<textformat leftmargin="5" rightmargin="5" leading="5"><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p><br/><p><b><font color="#ebe3cc">Antique time in the present</font></b></p><br/><p>This fascinating engraving reproduces an ancient Roman calendar,
etched into a tablet and discovered in 1547 by Bernadino Maffei, cardinal
of Rome. Three feet by two feet, the plinth is shown astride three pairs
of callipers, which indicate scale. Along the top row of the tablet, the
months, or what the Romans called calends, are indicated before their
name, topping twelve columns all starting with the letter K. Interesting
is the inscription "NON" which can be seen falling on the fifth or
seventh day of each month; this was an abbreviation for <i>nonus</i>
(ninth), a ritual day when the moon reached its first quarter phase.
</p><br/><p>Duchetti's print is remarkable for presenting the calendar as an
object rather then just information. Carefully delineating the tablet's
cracks and its roughened edges, the image is characteristic of an
increasing interest among Renaissance antiquarians in recording
extra-literary aspects of inscriptions.</p><br/><p>The famous Antwerp printer Plantin copied the print in 1574, but the
tablet itself was soon broken up and lost. A fragment survives today in
the Capitoline Museum in Rome.</p><br/><p><b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0120">More about
A120</a></font></b></p><br/><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p></textformat>]]></description>
<pid>speculum-0120-001</pid>
</slide>

<!-- 8 -->

<slide>
<title>Sources for art</title>
<name>C433</name>
<description><![CDATA[<textformat leftmargin="5" rightmargin="5" leading="5"><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p><br/><p><b><font color="#ebe3cc">Sources for art</font></b></p><br/><p>In this engraving an artist stands beneath a fanciful ruined arch,
engrossed in the reliefs above. This print was one of many published by
Androuet du Cerceau designed by Leonard Thiry. Thiry worked in Antwerp,
where he could have known Hieronymus Cock, and might have influenced
Cock's decision to concentrate on picturesque ruins as a print theme.
Like Cock's Colosseum views (e.g. <b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0212">B212</a></font></b>), Thiry's prints
invariably show ruins dotted with draughtsmen in action. Published in
many subsequent editions this print was also used for intarsia designs
in France and Southern Germany.</p><br/><p><b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0433">More about
C433</a></font></b></p><br/><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p></textformat>]]></description>
<pid>speculum-0433-001</pid>
</slide>

<!-- 9 -->

<slide>
<title>A Sculpture Garden</title>
<name>B240</name>
<description><![CDATA[<textformat leftmargin="5" rightmargin="5" leading="5"><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p><br/><p><b><font color="#ebe3cc">A Sculpture Garden</font></b></p><br/><p>Scholars are unclear whether this print describes an actual sculpture
garden, as its inscription suggests. It is likely based on a drawing by
Marten van Heemskerck; Hieronymus Cock, the publisher, carefully notes
his role as "printer" (<i>excu</i>) rather than inventor of the print
in italics at lower left. Draped male and female marbles, a sarcophagus,
column drums, entablatures, and a half-buried capitals lean against a
masonry wall and lay scattered in the foreground. We know that this
print was engraved by Lucas van Jan van Doetecum, a sibling team famed
for their ability to transcribe painterly shades of light and dark using
a mixed process of etching and engraving.</p><br/><p>The design makes little distinction between fragments of
architecture, sculpture, or funeraria, and the single bearded bystander,
who sits, right arm raised, on a collapsed column shaft ( <b><font color="#df790c"><a href="event:zoom?x=0.218&amp;y=0.036&amp;zoom=91">
Take a closer look.</a></font></b> ) is almost
indistinguishable from the other mutilated sculptures themselves.</p><br/><p><b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0240">More about
B240</a></font></b></p><br/><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | <a href="event:next"><b><font color="#df790c">next</font></b></a></p></textformat>]]></description>
<pid>speculum-0240-001</pid>
</slide>

<!-- 10 -->

<slide>
<title>Taking Ruins Home</title>
<name>C570</name>
<description><![CDATA[<textformat leftmargin="5" rightmargin="5" leading="5"><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | next</p><br/><p><b><font color="#ebe3cc">Taking Ruins Home</font></b></p><br/><p>In this engraving the Flemish artist Hendrick van Cleve has extracted
motifs from ruined Roman monuments and inserted them into a fantastic
Alpine landscape. Cleve made hundreds of drawings in Rome and nearby
Tivoli in the early 1550s. These were later excerpted in prints
published by the Collaert family.  The hemicylindrical temple and
obelisk were completely new motifs for many Northern European art
viewers, and would have been know solely though reproductions like the
<i>Speculum</i>.</p><br/><p>The copper plate for this print survived well into the seventeenth
century and was restruck several times. Flemish inventories list it as a
page from a <i>runenboeck</i>, or Book of Ruins, suggesting the potency
of the idea in popular imaginings of Rome.</p><br/><p><b><font color="#df790c"><a href="../search.php?detail=speculum-0570">More about
C570</a></font></b></p><br/><p align="right"><a href="event:previous"><b><font color="#df790c">previous</font></b></a> | next</p></textformat>]]></description>
<pid>speculum-0570-001</pid>
</slide>
</itinerary>
</itineraries>
